Society for New Music Archive
Society for New Music Archive
1971-2003
Society for New Music
12.5 linear ft.
Compositions, concert programs and newsletters from the Society for New Music, Syracuse NY.
2458922
Biographical History
[Taken from the Society's website, http://www.societyfornewmusic.org, 7 Nov 2005]
Founded in 1971, the Society's purpose is to act as a catalyst for the continued growth of the central New York musical community by commissioning new works, through advocacy (e.g. Society News and Fresh Ink on WCNY-FM and its Watertown and Utica affiliates), by featuring regional composers alongside guest composers, by providing regional musicians an opportunity to perform the music of their peers in order to gain new skills and techniques which they then share with their students, and by bringing new music to as broad an audience as possible through performances, broadcasts and cable TV.
The Society has grown from five concerts to approximately 25 per season, plus workshops and masterclasses, in addition to funding composers-in-residence in inner-city schools. The Society has participated in consortia with other groups throughout the U.S. for commissions, recordings, and exchanging performances and scores. In 1988/89, 1991/92, 1994/95 and 1996/97 the Society received ASCAP/Chamber Music America programming awards. In 1994 Neva Pilgrim and the Society received ACA's 'Laurel Leaf' Award. In 1999, the Society was chosen as the New York State representative for the national Continental Harmony Millennium commissioning project. In March 2001, the Society hosted the National SCI Conference. In 2001, the Society was honored with a NYS Governor's Arts Award, the only music organization among the 11 awardees.
The Society provides a format for living composers in the same way art galleries provide a format for visual artists, and is the only year-round new music organization in New York State outside of Manhattan. The Society annually awards the Brian M. Israel Prize to a composer 30 years of age or younger. The winner receives $500 and a performance. Honorable Mentions are also performed. Several winners have been women and minorities, most recently Evan Johnson, Huang Ruo, Winnie Cheung, Mark McConnell, Rob Paterson, and Derek Bermel.
The Society funds four composers in inner-city schools to work with 4th - 12th graders in writing new works for chorus, orchestra, and band, which are premiered by the students with professionals. This several-month project has students writing texts (language arts program), and setting them to music working in "composer teams" with the composer-in-residence. This program is so successful that composers and schools ask to be involved. Each year some problem students are re-labeled "gifted". The local media provides excellent coverage.
The Society commissions at least one new work each season and has produced four recordings and one CD of works by commissioned composers. The By-Laws of the Society stipulate that the organization commission regional composers. Commissioned composers have included women and minorities.
Since May 1996, the Society has produced Fresh Ink, a weekly program of recent music for WCNY-FM and its Watertown and Utica affiliates. It combines varied styles of new music into programs of interest to the listener, e.g. Sound Designs, Borrowed Music, Color Music, It's all Music, Cross-Cultural Cadences, etc., plus a new music calendar for all of upstate New York. CDs and DATs for this program have been submitted from around the globe.
Society News is published twice each season and mailed to a well-maintained list of 5,200 and includes information on concerts, composers, and a calendar of all new music concerts in central New York from Buffalo to Oneonta and Binghamton.
To attract an audience, the Society aims for a wide diversity of styles of recent music. The Society's vision is to provide enough opportunities in various contexts so people of all ages are conversant with the music of their own time. This translates into modest ticket prices, free concerts in extended-care facilities, libraries, galleries, and schools, plus programs with dance, theatre, poetry, film and/or art exhibits. The Society's Cazenovia Summer Series has expanded into a festival titled Cazenovia Counterpoint and spread over three weekends. In 2003, there were 20 events, 15 of which were free - all featuring new work by regional artists.
Over 20,000 people attend new music programs each season, plus weekly radio broadcasts, newsletter readers (10,500) and TV.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Society for New Music Archives is made up of two series, Compositions and Published Material. Compositions includes commissioned pieces and Brian M. Israel Prize winners from regional composers (one audiotape of one composition, the remainder are written scores). Published material includes a complete run of concert programs and announcements for seasons from 1971-2003, as well as issues of the Society's newsletter, Society Music (later rechristened Society News) and miscellaneous posters and promotional material.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Music; Society for New Music; Music, New York (State) -- Syracuse -- Societies, etc.; Music, New York (State) -- Syracuse -- 20th century.; Composers -- New York (State); Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Programs (documents); Scores.; Newsletters.; Composers.; Musicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Society for New Music
Inventory
- Compositions - commissioned pieces and Brian M. Israel Prize winners
  - Audio tape
    - Bialosky, Marshall
      - Birds, Bees, and Butterflies, and Far Theatricals of Day, undated (Box 1)
  - Scores
    - Bialosky, Marshall
      - Birds, Bees, and Butterflies, undated (Box 1)
        Conductor’s score
      - The Far Theatricals of Day, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Two Against One: Rhapsodic Episodes, 1989 (Box 1)
        Score for clarinet in BЬ
        Score for viola
    - Caltabiano, Ronald
      - Torched Liberty, undated (Box 1)
    - Clingan, Alton Howe
      - The Decay of the Angel, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Downing, Joseph
      - Partita # 6 – Appalachian Folk Song Suite, 1989 (Box 1)
        Conductor’s score with program and rehearsal notes
        Score for violin I
        Score for violin II
        Score for violoncello
    - Green, Michelle F.
      - Quid Pro Quo, 1990 (Box 1)
        Score for flute, and clarinet in BЬ
        Score for violin, and cello
    - Keyes, Christopher
      - O Sweet Spontaneous Earth, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Harris, Matthew
      - Starry Night, undated (Box 1)
        Score for violin
        Score for cello
    - Lefkowitz, David S.
      - Quartet for Flute, Violin, Cello & Piano, 1992 (Box 1)
        Score for flute
    - Lewis, Malcolm
      - And There Appeared Three Horsemen, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Liptak, David
      - Rhapsodies, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Morrill, Dexter
      - Six Dark Questions, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Morris, Robert
      - Society Sound, 2006 (Box 2)
        Score for flute, oboe, clarinet, violin, violincello
    - Palmer, Robert
      - String Quartet No. 5, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Pellman, Samuel
      - Crane Songs, undated (Box 2)
        Score for percussion
    - Rochberg, George
      - Phaedra, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
        Conductor’s score part 1
        Conductor’s score part 2
    - Sanchez-Gutierrez, Carlos
      - ...[and of course Henry the Horse] Dances the..., 2007 (Box 2)
        Score for piano duo, percussion duo, string quartet
    - Schramm, Betsy L.
      - And Birds are Wings Score for piano/celesta, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Sierra, Roberto
      - Tres Fantasías, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Silsbee, Ann
      - Wakings, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Stucky, Steven
      - Four Poems of A. R. Ammons, 1992 (Box 3)
      - Sappho Fragments, 1982 (Box 3)
        Score for flute/piccolo
        Score for piano
    - Thomas, Augusta Read
      - Angel Musings, 1996 (Box 3)
        First cadenza
        Second cadenza
        Score for bass
        Score for harp
        Score for solo guitar
    - Timpson, Michael Sidney
      - Mirrors of the Psyche, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Wagner, Melinda
      - Sextet, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Wernick, Richard
      - A Poison Tree, undated (Box 3)
    - Willey, James
      - Society Music, undated (Box 3)
        Score for horn in F
        Score for trombone
        Score for trumpet in BЬ
    - Yedida, Ron
      - Black Snow, 1987 (Box 3)
- Compositions - other works premiered by the Society for New Music
  - Scores
    - Phillips, Burrill
      - Letters from Italy Hill, 1984 (Box 3)
- Printed material
  - Concert programs and announcements
    - 1971-1972 season (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973 season (Box 4)
    - 1973-1974 season (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975 season (Box 4)
    - 1975-1976 season (Box 4)
    - 1976-1977 season (Box 4)
    - 1977-1978 season (Box 4)
    - 1978-1979 season (Box 4)
    - 1979-1980 season (Box 4)
    - 1980-1981 season (Box 4)
    - 1981-1982 season (Box 4)
    - 1982-1983 season (Box 4)
    - 1983-1984 season (Box 4)
    - 1984-1985 season (Box 5)
    - 1985-1986 season (Box 5)
    - 1986-1987 season (Box 5)
    - 1987-1988 season (Box 5)
    - 1988-1989 season (Box 5)
    - 1989-1990 season (Box 5)
    - 1990-1991 season (Box 5)
    - 1991-1992 season (Box 6)
    - 1992-1993 season (Box 6)
    - 1993-1994 season (Box 6)
    - 1994-1995 season (Box 6)
    - 1995-1996 season (Box 6)
    - 1996-1997 season (Box 7)
    - 1997-1998 season (Box 7)
    - 1998-1999 season (Box 7)
    - 1999-2000 season (Box 7)
    - 2000-2001 season (Box 7)
    - 2001-2002 season (Box 7)
    - 2002-2003 season (Box 7)
  - Newsletters
    - "Society Music"
      - v. 1-v.4, 1986 –1988 (Box 8)
    - "Society News"
      - v.4- v.16, 1989 –2001 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous posters and promotional material (Box 9)